thank you okay no no yeah maybe just
worth as I said briefly before just
saying that this is where we're talking
to quite a broad audience here so this
conversation is going to be trance you
know we're going to create it into
something but yeah it's for it's for a
very broad audience and some of that
audience won't have much understanding
about regenerative cultures so we want
to make it as not simplify it but make
it translatable for them so they're just
to kind of frame that
so the first yeah the first question and
kind of my curiosity as much as anybody
else's is I'm curious about your story
and how you started working with the
concept of regenerative cultures and why
yeah how did that how did that happen
well thank you and it's a good place to
start because for me a lot of what
regenerative practice is all about is
personal development like it starts in
everybody's individual story and how
they find their calling and their
essence and then try to express it in
the world and so I when I do interviews
with people who I consider elders in the
regenerative movement I often ask them
to start with the personal story so
thank you and I've said this before like
basically I'm I I started like I'm a
German originally and I wanted to be a
marine biologist and to study whales and
dolphins and ended up with every
University studying biology and um and
then went to California my undergrad get
to do some research on dolphins and also
an elephant seals and I had this moment
at one point where I asked myself with
everything that's going on in the world
these animals that are so loved and that
I want to dedicate my life to am I most
likely not going to be here when my
grandchildren grow up because of our
actions and then I in a thought of
because I don't have this like am I
going to go into primatology or Sea
apes or dolphins and two of my great
heroes were Jane Goodall Dian Fossey and
they're very different characters Jane
Goodall is the saintly nonviolent person
who just will do her work and has been
for many decades carrying an amazing
message and Dian Fossey was more of a
fiery activist type that that when when
people started to encroach on the
gorillas she was studying she kind of
tried to like play witchcraft and scare
them and they they got scared and they
fought back and they killed her and and
and so I asked myself what would I do
with something happen to these animals
would I have the capacity to be like
Jane Goodall and and I'm probably not at
the time I was too too fiery and I felt
I was more of a than Fauci type and and
somehow that at that point I made a
decision that it was not my sensible
that the best thing I could do for the
dolphins was actually to work on my own
species you look at sustainability and
that's what what we're calling it
and and that started me on a long
journey I did a master's in holistic
science at Omaha College in 2001 and
that's where really clicked on the power
of design like learning from elders like
John Todd and David or how design was so
much more than I thought it was about I
also thought because I was just sort of
making things look pretty so quiet but
that design is actually just human
intention on our worldview and what we
think we need and what we truly need
translated into somehow us shaping the
world around us to meet those needs and
we need to really pay attention how we
do that because if we do it one way we
messed things up pretty badly and so in
2006 I because I always wanted to do
this big mapping of how all of this fits
together
so identity tents and and so I wrote
this 750 pH pH D thesis called design
for human and Planetary
of a holistic in tabular approach to
complexity and sustainability but this
this was like this whole academic bit
came after I actually spent two years
travelling around in a van
visiting eco villages visiting cats
doing multiple courses at the Center for
alternative technology in techniques
doing long-term volunteer programs
they're going to find' horn going to the
Layton's garden in Germany or to
determine who in Italy all the different
eco villages and then I moved to region
and southern Spain and in Juarez where
back in 1999 I wanted to set up an
environmental education center and and
eco village - as I was calling it then
live the solutions rather than be part
of the problem and honestly like I did
all the things that for many people I've
seen so many people do it since it's
this dream where you just want to bring
your best friends together and live ever
after and and you completely think
you'll never have any problems and and
and also I still thought it was all
about Strawberry buildings and compost
blues and and solar panels and then I
realized wow this is much more complex
there's a human dimension that I have
absolutely zero idea about how to how to
work with the team how to make decisions
in a circle and also the economic
dimensions just just basically how do I
finance this project and how do we make
a healing project in a degenerative
economy that is structurally twisted and
wrong and so yeah
this journey into maja college and all
this academia was really the the
practical activist hippy wanting to
learn more how to do it properly and and
of course then I lost myself a little
bit in the heavy academia stuff but in
2006 when my PhD was finished no funding
council would have funded the extremely
transdisciplinary research and applied
research that I wanted to do now that
would be different but
the reason that that happened kind of
pushed me I'm glad now life is always
like that one door closes another opens
pushed me to site then I ended up at
Finland I'm doing the very first eco
village design education course that by
education just launched and we did a
training of trainers there and realized
that that was a map that was so similar
like I actually knew that before that's
why I did the course because at 2005
when they first introduced the the
curriculum idea and Wow that's what I'm
working on in my PhD and so the reason
why I went to Finland to do the course
was to see how this group of educators
out of the kind of eco village activism
movement had brought together practices
in the same sort of theoretical
framework that I was working around my
PhD and so when I did that course I did
it more to see how they were teaching it
rather than what the content was and and
ever since then I've been working with
Gaia education and and putting all the
kind of more backed up content with lots
of books to read and and the stories
told of people having done it before
that we can learn from em and I've been
writing that into Gaia education work so
I helped to write the content of their
online course and and that's really
traveled now all over the world and yeah
I said to keep it short I spent I spent
ten years after that putting things into
action living at film home for four
years then I've moved here to Majorca
because I'm interested in by a regional
scale change and I'm just on a journey I
really think it's it's an ongoing
apprenticeship in pilgrimage that that
we're all on to somehow understand how
can we best serve and since my book came
out I've realised that there is a power
in social media of just putting the
stuff out there to start conversations
and then trust that people pick it up
and because it's I love questions rather
than answers I think we jump to
smoothing far too quickly apps
because the minute you give people a
question to ask then you really want
them to involve themselves you're asking
them is this meaningful to me what have
I could contribute to them like it
join the conversation if you give them a
principle and they they kind of I'm
asked to say I agree with that principle
when I join you yeah that's great I mean
there's so much there that I resonate
with personally and especially that I
feel like questions are a doorway into
into learning aren't they like if you
have a statement then it's kind of like
it's a bit harder to unpack that
statement and kind of learn about it
whereas if you have a question you have
to arrive at the statement yourself and
that journey is there I feel like is the
growth is the development and we I'm
yeah I'm really interested in that and
also what you say about yeah we all have
this dream of starting an eco village or
a you know beautiful community and it's
so right that the interpersonal human
dynamics are just as much part of that
as any kind of structural economic
aspect and so it's really great to hear
you name that so in a few sentences how
might you explain what regenerative
cultures is to someone who's like never
heard about it who may be yeah I'm not
going to give more context just like
someone who's never heard about who's
heard about the context the concept not
necessarily an easy question it's a
question of course that I get asked a
lot and I'm trying to get the same
answer and bring it different wants to
it yeah again I think it is actually a
process of inquiry like we're just
talking about questions and so it's it's
a continuous personal and team or
community based inquiry into how we can
bring out the unique essence and
opportunity that is our unique gift that
when each person has has has just
there's nothing nothing like you there's
nothing like me another time in the
world or nobody and we are unique and
and how do we create a culture where
people can really contribute that
uniqueness in ways to the larger whole
their community their ecosystem the
biosphere in ways that also bring out
the the maximum potential of that whole
community so how do we participate well
in life how do we as Janine Benyus from
biomimicry as put it beautifully life
creates conditions conducive to life the
regenerative culture is constantly on
the on the quest of understanding how do
i best create conditions conducive to
life always sort of myself how do I
serve my community and how do I serve
the community of life in in everything I
do and and so it's that's why I'm so
adamant that that this is a process of
inquiry that is connected to place and
therefore it will be different in each
place culture it's it's a plural because
it will come out slightly differently
because it's the essence that informs us
it's placed sourced it comes out of like
even within the UK it will look
different in Devon than in Sussex right
and but of course that for me the
underlying pattern is disability - how
do we how do we draw from the wisdom of
many work voices and how do we when we
see that there are seeming reconcilable
opposites of opinion how do we what
other people put them in a box stop
listening to them label them because
they just said a trigger word that we
are against all isn't competing utterly
against all forms of capital
and he still thinks capitalism could be
redesigned hence and stopped talking to
this person because he's not bought it
yeah well he doesn't say it's all done
it'll collapse and therefore he's in
denial and um stop talking to me to
really stay in the process and say what
is this person why are they thinking
this to stay in that dialogue and to see
that in what seems like irreconcilable
opposites there's potential for a higher
level resolution of that that we can
only get to if we stay open to the
conversation and for me that's like
understanding that life is a planetary
process and we are one in the same time
emergent properties just parts of that
process that pop out but we are all
because we are part everything we do
like this conversation but every action
that you do in the rest of you if this
day affects that larger hole that is
also you and so once we get that
responsibility of saying okay it's not
about the weather
I changed the world or not just by being
I am changing the world so how do I be
not just do but be in a way that I do so
wisely for the future of all life and
that that's for me at the core of of
this inquiry process of regenerative
cultures but of course there are lots of
different facets that we can yeah I
really
I've been reading adrien-marie Browns
the commercient strategy and the thing
that's really set out with me from that
is the yeah this micro and macro scale
and what I choose to embody on the micro
will affect the macro in this this kind
of relationship between them this is
really great to hear you speak about
that and yeah I really I'm experiencing
that actually and I think I'm seeing a
lot of people around me also
experiencing that they're kind of like
clicking that inquiry of like this isn't
just about like
making the changes out there happen but
it's about how we create those changes
both as individuals and collectives yeah
yeah maybe another thing that's really
an important thing and that's that's
that's a tricky one to stick with this
paradox because on the one hand yes of
course we have a planetary emergency and
that is a problem like climate change is
a problem cascading ecosystems collapse
is a massive problem
an obscene inequality is a massive
problem but truly regenerative practice
doesn't start from problem mindsets
but from potential mindsets it's it's
about finding out what can happen when
we think differently and therefore begin
to bring forth the world differently
together in the the thought of here's a
problem we need to solve it let's
declare war on climate change that's not
going upstream enough to really say it's
the mindset of problem solution war
against it is part of what got us in the
first place you if you follow climate
change upstream then you see okay this
is cascading ecosystems collapse that
has been gone going on for centuries
this is nothing new and like even before
we started burning fossil fuels with
agriculture and and with with like it's
just looking into a project in in
Siberia yesterday that is rewilding a
massive area of Siberia but bringing
back the herds of ungulates that early
humans killed off and therefore changed
the vegetation patterns there and
changed and the whole climate like that
the fact that when we started hunting
whales before fossil fuels for fuel that
was made out of the whale blubber and
more the the species from the sperm
whales and that already affected climate
because the whales got a nutrient pumps
in the oceans and without and the whales
and taking krill at the bottom like
in the deeper areas and then coming up
the surface to breathe in pooping and
they fertilize the upper water that then
enables more of that mountain to grow
that they later feed on but in the
process they they're massive carbon
cycles in the oceans and so so we really
need to understand these larger
processes in which which we are part of
and but then if we go further upstream
like an the canonic system that we've
got has driven a lot of that kind of
behavior of destroying the planet
but really that's also just a symptom
like the way we designed our economic
system the mistaken form of the
extractive capitalism that we've got
right now and that is structurally
dysfunctional and unless we change it
we're not going to fundamentally get
different solutions but ultimately it's
on our hearts and our minds ultimately
it's it's a story about worldview values
and the narrative the answers we give to
the question Who am I where am I going
where do I come from individually and
and and collectively and to ask like my
took my book I wrote it somewhat
triggered by the one question that my
mentor David all asked me in 2006 he
said he said I mean before we find out
how to create a human presence on earth
that is sustainable we need to ask a
deeper question and that is what is it
about being human that makes us worth
being sustained are we worth it and if
we have a answer to that question from
that place in each place place or stand
culture so we can create wonderful
expressions of why we are worth it but
we need then also to my mind understand
the diversity that we saw cherish as
biodiversity is also expressed in us and
life in our diversity of opinions and so
how do we build a future together while
we still disagree on a lot of things
because I think we'll always disagree
yeah it's like that's neat there's like
doesn't need it we need it like a meta
approach in order to be able to meet
each other in the disagreements and not
like dip into this kind of canceling
culture of like you say that words so
therefore I won't associate myself with
you but actually to stay open even
though there might be disagreement I
think that's like a huge yeah like a
huge there's work needed there that you
know you know when you say about
personal development like that takes
work you know but when you do it when
you do that you probably experienced it
yourself if you try to build a bridge
between two camps that are a bit
opposing what you find very quickly is
you get shot at from both sides of the
bridge because in trying to make them
understand a little bit more where they
are coming from you sound like them and
get attacked and even enjoy and like
vice versa so it that's the sort of
being aware that that's gonna keep
happening and still sitting in the fire
as Anna Mendell calls it with
process-oriented psychology sitting in
that fire saying okay let's meet in our
disagreement find that higher ground
from which we can unleash the potential
that that is actually an inhumanity to
true and this is what I believe we need
to do ultimately that's what
regenerative cultures everywhere would
achieve to my mind is to redesign the
human impact on earth within the
lifetime of the Genet generations alive
today from being exploitative and
extractive and degenerative to being
healing and regenerative we we are not
the cancer on the earth we can be a
healing power if we keep telling the
story that humans bad always bad we will
never unleash the potential that we have
in and we have the responsibility
because we missed what the system so
badly that we can't just now walk away
and say it's Zenda the adult generation
saying look at the data generation they
will solve it and you know we're all in
this together absolutely great
I think you just answered I kind of I
had a question
how you know why is this an important
thing for us to incorporate within our
activism and more broadly within our
work towards a better future but I think
you've sort of named it there but do you
feel like there's something there that
you would like to respond to anyway
wait for me and I paid drift for me the
biggest hope of what what we need to
somehow nurture like it if you mentioned
briefly complexity and like complex
dynamic systems and you can experience
them with more than three interacting
variables is a complex dynamic system
that means every cell in your body every
organ your body as a whole and your
family your community ecosystems the
planet and they're all nested and
they're all the boundaries we put on
them every thing I just mentioned is
next it and part of the larger and in
this complexity is fundamentally
unpredictable and uncontrollable that
means the idea of designing cultures is
a paradox because on the one hand you
can't design culture because because
culture emerges out of the relationships
and the interactions and then
information that flows through the
system and it's about the quality and
not quantity of relationships and
information that really affects what
emerges and so so we if we try to
positively affect what's going on in
this larger system that we're trying to
have a healing influence on then for me
that one of the biggest steps right now
is to link those people activated by X
are those people activated by Friday is
for the future there's a huge amount of
people all over the globe young people
and all the people that that have
finally got that there is it's not about
spectator anymore it's we're all having
to step on the stage and play this
kind of epic act of ulsan Humanity is
transforming itself last minute to
respond to a crisis that could mean the
end of humanity and the end of much life
on earth and that that's the the big
epic that that will play out this
century and um what we meet is right now
in my view you know that there's a lot
of people in exile who already talk
about solutions but the perception right
now is we're just saying I want you to
panic or there's a problem and there's
an emergency it's it's focused on the
problem if we could connect that whole
movement to the wonderful regenerative
cultures that already exist which is a
movement which is the reshare movement
which is the Eco village movement the
permaculture movement the agroforestry
movement but also in the social
dimensions there's so much already their
cultures not just I mean it sound like
courses you know like nonviolent
communication but really there's a whole
culture of people that are trained in
that and know about it there's a whole
culture of socialist people and
holacracy people there's a culture of
people who work with integral theory and
in each one of them there are people who
are completely ready to step up and
share these and facets of regenerative
cultures emerging in all their diversity
and if we can connect all the people who
now want to make a difference to these
practical ways of making the difference
of learning these capacities doing stuff
on the ground and asking the question in
a sort of transition town plus plus plus
way and that actually plays Aikido with
sustainable development goals and
doesn't say oh that's a top-down UN
process don't want anything to do with
it I can of course no actually I can use
the SDGs to have a conversation with
with Town Hall and with businesses in
this region because they committed to it
and then I can use that as the entry
point but begin by by having a
conversation because you see the human
relationships and and make these people
shift a little bit and start a different
type of dialogue which is more about how
do we come together
to regenerate this place so and for me
that to lodge extend education is
central there so if we only managed to
map out an alternative to going to
university to all those school kids who
are on Fridays for future demonstrations
and say you can take a four-year
apprenticeship where you go to
ecosystems restoration comes and
ecovillages and you do online courses
and you travel and you learn a few
languages and you build capacity in
yourself in relationship and you will
come out four years later with less debt
and much more experience more employable
or you might not want to be employed you
might co-create something and with the
people you met on the way and that good
yeah
so it's a regenerative culture is for me
the step beyond we need a rebellion and
we need to do something it's this is
what we need to do right yeah that's
really beautiful way of putting it and
part of the team I'm involved with are
working on a way to offer that so it's
really it's really timely to hear you
say that because that's that is
something that has felt yeah like
potentially missing it's like okay we've
recognizing that there's a problem
there's people that are becoming
activated and waking up to this but then
how do you guide them and support them
into that co-creation of the future we
want to see and I think you know you've
just answered that one brief thing
because if the word activated and I got
this piece or medium that speaks that is
also in my book but it's it's a story
that and I got as I said I've worked for
a long time still work with them a
little bit good and guy education who
might some extent be because I've been
on this for a long time this mapping and
making people aware of what's all out
there and how it all fits together in a
bigger puzzle and and so in many ways
the the guy education online course
design for sustainability is one of
those it takes you through these four
dimensions social ecological economic
and worldview and in that open
boxes where you where you begin to be
aware oh there's dragon dreaming there's
social history there's alternative
currencies there's transition towns
there's this regenerative communities
network or the ecosystems right that
they're all mapped for people so they
and then they can go wherever like
deepen wherever they feel attracted to
but the the person that I worked with
amused the current CEO a guy education
may East and at one point we were
running a training together and and she
said to me one morning you know I still
see my like this is a while ago she said
I still see myself as an activist but
for me activism is about getting up
every morning and after my morning
meditation ask myself the question what
do I want to activate power of my
intention and the power of my spirit my
by breath where do I want to give my
energy to and what conversations do I
want to activate do I want to activate
the yes let's kill all the 1% they're
the evil ones instead although I want to
activate the story of is there
possibility to transform all of humanity
and come from life generating conditions
can you see is there a place beyond
mother ring can we engage everyone
somehow it's two different stories to
actively it's the story of am i separate
from everyone and the world is just
showing me and and and and fight the
world and complain about the situation
we're in or activate the story of
interbeing that that everything is an
opportunity to engage and and that why
we can't choose to large extent what's
happening to us we can choose the
attitude we take towards how we respond
what's helping for us and that changes
everything and so there's this reframing
of activism as what am i activating by
the language I use the thought forms I
repeat the reactions I do
I love that that's so that's so
brilliant I'm going to be taking that
and putting it in my pocket thank you
so yeah so we you mentioned the Fridays
for future movement there's you know
there is through the work of various
different movements and extinction
rebellion I think there is a lot of fear
and uncertainty about the future there
is of this this kind of like yeah sense
of form of like foreboding that's
happening and yeah that fear and incest
fee there's a lot better the youth as
well so how would you see the work of
regenerative coaches supporting people
in a post climate change world like if
we if that happens if that doom and
gloom that is being spoken about arrives
like what is the role that regenerative
cultures plays in that in that
possibility I think that's another one
of those where we instead of having
interesting conversations about the
dynamics and the potential that right
like in which as a biologist
look how evolution happens and how
novelty emerges then collapse breakdown
death has always been part of that life
as a planetary process like that the
German poet scientists greater said more
than two hundred years ago and that
death is life's ingenious way of
creating plenty of life and and to some
extent Joanna Macy put it in it in this
wonderful term of saying um we have a
dual role where were hospice workers to
a dying system and midwives of a system
that wants to be born yeah hospice
workers of the industrial growth society
and midwives of the life-sustaining or
generative culture future and so I think
the jury is still out of whether we can
even reverse global warming by doing the
right actions at the right scale geo
therapy not geoengineering and to draw
down vast amounts of carbon into soils
standing forests for functional wetlands
and mangroves and begin to heal the
damage that we've done over 5,000 years
and I think that the pathway towards
doing that is exactly the same pathway
as the pathway when you said okay what's
the other option
it's too late we're running into a
future where basically over 300 300 400
years we just know it's always gonna get
worse and and there's a few generations
left to live out our species on on on on
a system that is in meltdown if we were
to prepare for that future the wisest
way of doing that would also be to come
back to place to region to refit how we
meet our needs to the unique conditions
of the bio regions we we live in and to
regional eyes production and consumption
wherever possible to diversify our local
economies in on ways that we basically
have the resilience that we can meet
most of the coordinates in the bio
region but in ways that are aimed at
healing and making the bio region as
resilient as possible so it is also
about reforesting and shifting towards
the biomaterials economy and and a
circle like circular biomaterials
economy shifting away from materials
that come out of the ground that need
high amounts of energy to be pulled out
all all these
kind of things if we prepare on the
ground if we make sure that we build
food sovereignty water sovereignty
educational sovereignty energy
sovereignty of renewables at the
regional scale it still needs massive
amount of other changes often consuming
less so differently but I think these
two paths are actually converging so in
in the sense that the more people we get
on the path of healing their region Co
creatively having the conversation of
what would a regenerative culture in
this place looked like what did this
place look like in the past how M but it
but also combining ancient wisdom with
modern technology in a way that finds
that potential of a both/and rather than
an either/or and so that for me is like
it's it's defeatist to say that we're
definitely had it I think we there is
still a real chance to make a difference
and at the same time we need to embrace
collapse as because so much of the
collapse we will see around us is the
collapse of patterns and processes that
are dysfunctional and no longer work
it's the dissolution of rigidity and it
happens the same way in in ecosystems
like the climax ecosystem isn't as
creative as a patch in a climate
ecosystem that has been disturbed and
weather like trees have fallen over a
storm has come through that's where a
lot of the buzz happens and and in many
ways we I mean it's also being aware
that that path of planetary healing will
take us at least three to four decades
and even if we do it
mobilized by price for future and ex-ira
and everybody else was trying to
mobilize different layers of societies
from different storytelling memes and if
we achieve it that we create a level of
human collaboration at a globe
called scale local and global at the
same time to do this everywhere it will
still mean that over the next 10-15
years things are probably gonna get
worse we have gonna see more storms
we're gonna see because there's a lag in
the climate system that even if we do
all the right things now we're still
gonna see more collapse and that then
needs a level of maturity of
understanding that this work is
intergenerational long term work it's
like a secular building work we started
maybe the next generation finishes it if
we do it well the next three decades are
gonna be a tough ride no matter what
because we left too late but to say the
next three decades are just riding it
out and it's definitely gonna go to
shit's afterwards I think it's mistaken
tour and and I think that this
unfortunately a few we were talking
about ego trips is that there's a few
people that because it's sort of prop
being a profit of doing immediately
gives you a share lots of attention and
and I find that's really dangerous
like I like I'm all for eepa adaptation
and but it's been misunderstood by a lot
of people as it's all over and prepare
for the massive collapse and and it's a
bit more nuanced than that some
collapses and some like breakdowns and
breakthroughs at the same time mmm it's
such a great way of framing it like that
for me it fills me with like I haven't
heard it explained or put like that in a
way because I feel like I'm interacting
with a lot of people where that it is it
is doomed
it is gloom but to him you put it in
that way I feel not a sense of hope like
blind hope but like ah there's there's
more here it's a more long-term story
we're playing rather than this short
term we need these demands met in this
amount of time we need we also need a
longevity towards that work
[Music]
add another nuance to this and because
it is also like about understanding the
difference between doing and being
and I mean this might sound really
philosophical but ultimately I mean I
always reminded for me this was today
it just speaks to that and you know the
wonderful work Joanna Macy has done in
translating Lukas poems and there's this
beautiful poem that I wrote almost 100
years ago
dear darkening ground where he was
basically speaking about this time and
and and at the end of that poem he asks
give me just a little more time give me
just a little more time so I may love
the things until they're real and ripe
and worthy of you and and that's a shift
in being that's a shift in understanding
that the way that we can hold the
uncertainty of whether we're going to
make it the actual fact that we don't
have that certainty is what's cooking us
to the point that we are actually
transforming as beings it is a
species-level rite of passage by
confronting the possibility of
extinction at the species level we're
now pushed each individually to take a
step of maturation and ask how do we
become mature members in the community
of life how do we serve life rather than
let life serve us and understand that in
serving life we serve ourselves because
we are live and and and that is a being
change that ultimately says it doesn't
matter whether we're gonna make it or
not it matters how we go out if we go
out and it matters how we go forward if
we go forward and that's about coming
back to the gift that is just this
conversation that we're having here
right now like being in relationship is
what life is all about and and so the
minute we act from that state of being
where we're actually not attached to
outcomes and we love the fact that we
get the opportunity to be here and
respond
this transformational moment in human
history in the history of life where
where ultimately what's also happening
at the same time is answering the
question why are we worth it we begin to
realize that we are life's way of
experiencing self I mean of course it
sequoia tree or penguin also is life's
way of experiencing itself but but the
level of human consciousness that can
put the love for a forest into a song
and that all the things that can risk
your life direct nonviolent direct
actions they're all the beautiful images
of X are where people have found that
strength that courage to step up and act
from a power that is beyond their
individual because again Joanna Macy
said this to me at one point she said
think Daniel when you do these actions
do them with the authority of 3.8
billion years of life's evolution when
you stand on that stage and you tell
people it's not Daniel Valle talking in
your ego blah blah blah it's life
speaking to life and if we come from
that place then then it's it's a very
different that's that's where the
regeneration happens yeah I'm really
feeling the like thank you well so I had
a couple of questions that were I was
trying I was basically trying to put
myself in the shoes of people that
they're a variety of different people so
say like the old person that is not so
mobile or and is just starting to find
out these about these issues and doesn't
have a community around them or the the
single mother that's living in a tower
block that's like working pretty
intensely in order to look after her
family I was trying to put myself in
those different shoes and think like
what would those people ask an expert
about regenerative cultures like what
would what would they want to know so
I've got a couple of questions that are
specifically from that
so I was imagining it like if I wanted
to help support my local community to
become more regenerative and I'm not
sure how to start or to do that in a way
that's respectful for everyone's
differences what would you do in a
situation like that what what advice
would you give well first I really have
to respond okay
I think we we're making a mistake by
repeating the the meme of expert
cultures like I don't I don't see myself
and as as an expert and well I spend a
lot of time on that apprenticeship and
have learned a lot from amazing people
that that that I can share little
snippets of insights that other people
have given me inside myself but but
really I think that all of us have if we
and it's difficult I mean this is that
for me personally something really big
happened when my daughter was born in
the last like she's not two and a half
years old and I kind of realized only
through her how somewhat arrogant I had
become in my own privilege with every
education that I've had and all the the
privilege of having been able to live my
life the way of lived ISM and do all
this and um and it was quite judgmental
of Joe Bloggs like sometimes I would sit
in on a bus and I'd hear people talk
about whatever the current
binge-watching telenovela whatever was
on like I live in Spain and yeah but
since I become a father I realize how
easy it is to be in the treadmill of
this degenerative system that that that
is still active out there and when you
look okay with all the love that you
look at your children the priority that
they're fed in in school and that
they're well and
between the dynamics of partnership and
friends and families around that life
can very quickly swallow you up in a way
that to point at people and say we
should be doing more for the saving the
planet is a bit arrogant
and and and and so but at the same time
I do feel that that we all simply by by
having the quack at the conversations
it's the conversation with some other
mothers while you're waiting for it to
come out of school or to just ask these
questions that there are about how could
we live differently and see all these
people in the street can we can we not
what is it that we can do about it maybe
we should ask the school to do a bit
more with the parents they need to
respond to us and and and to also be
aware that I that no matter how tight
the financial situation is every time we
spend into this economic system we're
driving Italy even if we spend
positively if we try to be good
consumers and buy the right products and
stuff we're still because they're the
money system is in itself degenerative
and that we that's another story we need
to somehow change that as well but but
we still have a choice like consumer
cooperatives are popping up everywhere
that make local organic food affordable
and and even make it the entry point
into that conversation like just saying
I want to do more and and say how do I
do that and to bring a few other people
together and say how do we pool our
resources so we can buy a local organic
food can we find a farmer or because
they almost and now they're community
supported agriculture systems popping up
and if you don't have the money to pay
the whole ledge box you can you can you
can come on a Sunday with your family
and and do some some farming so it's
it's basically because what's coming is
going to be a bit of a rocky ride
coming back to community is the most
important thing and to find others and
engage with them in conversation and I
think that children food and health a
wonderful entry points to that nested
wholeness to understanding all the other
bits like when you come into food you
understand how it's linked to your
personal health how it's linked to
ecosystems health where it comes from
and so easy to from just entering with
what do we eat at home to completely
rebuild your entire worldview almost
when when you understand it amazing
yeah great way to articulate that and
really yeah really clear thank you and
so then I was thinking I was also
thinking about some of the critiques of
extra and yeah I was just I was thinking
about climate justice and it's really
important to a lot of people within and
outside of the movement and you know
there's a critique around Exxon and its
whiteness and its privilege how my
regenerative cultures support us or
support support as I say us as in XR but
I think us more wired widely to within
climate justice and within that that
part of the movement towards a more
beautiful future that's a huge one and
then and again it's very difficult
because you've got an overeducated over
privileged white guy in the second half
of his 40s in front with you and so I'm
kind of I'm one of the exact examples of
what people might be reacting against of
we need more middle-aged white guys to
tell us what to do and
it's dead there's a lot of trauma of all
the people within each culture in each
country we've had like the xenophobia is
popping up so strongly and I'm
originally from Germany to see that in
Germany there's a rise of fascism and
and neo-nazis again I really thought
that wasn't gonna happen again
we were pretty strongly educated about
the atrocities that happened in in
Germany and in before and during the
Second World War and to see that that
evil monster is rearing its head all
over the world and how of course we need
to stand up to that and um and and it's
so difficult to still stay in that place
of not uttering not again out of even
out of that making a box and not seeing
these people anymore because that just
perpetuates the the the process and and
what I find like recently I had a
conversation with Joel glance Burke was
one of the real elders in in the
Regenesis Institute in a Genesis group
kind of carry the lineage of how to use
regenerative practice to change how
people think to change the processes
behind and and he pointed out workers we
were talking about D colonialization we
were talking about that even that D like
D gross D colonialization is again this
polarizing all the swing in the pendulum
other
like it's it's recalling like our minds
have been colonialist all our minds the
white minds as well and one thing that
he pointed out historically
which is really interesting is that it's
not as simple as just saying all the
white guys from Europe were the colonial
Isis and went everywhere and fucked up
the planet and and now
climate change is happening and it was
mainly those cultures that caused 90% of
it and it it's hitting all the the
cultures that actually had less to do
with it and many of these cultures and
that is a fact in history that that
first we exploited raped and pillaged in
colonialism then we exploited raped and
pillaged in neo colonialism with
neoliberal economics and and
globalization and now climate change is
hitting the same places really hard and
there's a sort of attitude of oh we lend
you some money to solve the problems
mmm that's crazy but to be mindful of
the fact that like Joel said this when
all these Americans like when America
was colonialist by European settlers a
vast amount of the people that actually
went over there were indentured that
means that some rich guy brought 50 or
60 people over paying for that passage
and then they needed to serve that
person for seven years in order to pay
for that patented passage and this was
at a time where people live generally
into their early 40s so it was a big
chunk of their life and what what he was
trying to point out was that actually
most of the white guys the trauma of
being oppressed and being slaves
happened in the white culture just as
much they were also slaves and if Hugh
de l'europe was basically futile slavery
like there was a land Lordan and so I
think we need to realize that it's not
as simple of just just because you have
a different skin color you the oppressed
and and and if you white you're you're
the oppressor
and it's to understand that this pattern
of oppression and of other ring runs
through all the cultures and that we
need to address these issues but by just
other ring again it
it's not going to help resolve it but
again I'm I'm very aware that I'm
probably triggering a lot of people in
minority cultures by what I've just said
because um if you've been subjected to
physical violence and psychological
violence how you look or who you love or
how about my sexuality is or whatever
and it's completely understanding that
you carry so much trauma and so much
anger that when you say who are you to
tell me I can't other this fuckhead my
girlfriend and just for how she looks or
something yeah I understand that that
people hold that energy but but I think
that for me regenerative cultures is
also about taking a deep dive into this
but really listening
from a place of interbeing from from
actually feeling the pain of that other
person deeply inside like there's
there's this beautiful beautiful poem by
tip not han and call me by my true names
yeah and I you can find it just google
call me by my true names for kidnet Han
that for me is the essence that if every
anybody who wants to have that
conversation about decolonial izing
exile and so on
just put that poem in your pocket
whenever there's an argument and you
feel like like that the energy flows up
let's just just right bring the
mindfulness fell in and read the poem to
everyone and you to yourself as well and
it will diffuse that conversation a
little bit wise words yeah I mean it's a
really charged subject and I think it's
a it's like there's a clear there's like
a plural versity of approaches to it and
I think yeah it's great to hear you
speak on that and speak about the need
to yeah that needs to find find a way to
see see the overview and how how do we
move past that so my final question what
would be the burning thing that you want
to say to extinction rebellion like if
we were all listening which we are what
but yeah what is the what is the burning
thing that feels really alive for you
that you'd like to say 2x huh
thank you thank you no I seriously I
mean it and I mean I don't I don't
distinguish as much between XR and
Fridays for future although I know that
but for me that movement that surging up
of life like what Paul Hawken call it a
long time ago a planetary immune
response and for me something really
shifted both in the first X our actions
here in Palma and the first Friday's for
a future demonstration to see that
finally there were so many others of us
in the street and and speaking up for
life as life and really touched me
deeply and and really made me feel
hopeful that that we're really now at at
this point of deep transformation that
the compost building that has been going
on for at least 50 years like well right
now a lot of people talk about all the
the big corporate you about like the big
oil companies nearby the land age 50
years ago of course they did but for 50
years like I know people who wrote the
briefing paper to the 1972 conference on
the environment my second PhD supervisor
John Todd I remember when I asked him 15
years ago what was it like back then in
1972 or when you started the new alchemy
Institute where the first experiments
about windmills and and and and all that
which he came from and he he said well
back then we were there were 50 60 of us
and we kind of knew each other by name
and and now there are millions yeah and
and the jump that has happened just in
line in 2019 and with
so many more people being aware of the
need for transformative change now but
but then I would say thank you and I
would also say um the biggest challenge
is how do we see the individual human
being who cares in all those different
because it's not just in the grassroots
movements that that this planetary
immune response is coming up there are
actually people in the large corporates
who have the same life speaking and
moving in them and wanting to make a
difference they and their mindsets their
and their friends mm-hmm
but there are people in the we mean
business Alliance the B team that
Richard Branson put together and yes of
course it's obscene how inequality and
how rich he is and all that but em how
do we how do we engage everybody like I
I find it really frustrating this wrong
kind of green movements that that just
shoots down the conversation about the
new Green Deal and all of that and and
immediately like all the kind of people
who are still trapped in the technology
will ride over the hill and save us
story there are lots of people who are
actually working on pretty useful things
for the transition like it's not quite
so clean cut to to actually keep seeing
the positive in these impulses and
trying to engage them because if we're
understanding that we're all kind of
from our limited perspectives all half
right and half wrong and trying to do
something about it and start walking in
the same direction that higher ground
together it's so much easier to then
have the conversation you still don't
get it there's something wrong with the
capitalist system as we have it right
now but then to maybe have the skillful
means of say saying let's not big devil
everybody who uses the word capital and
and
reclaim that and refrain that and and
work with that energy so this it's it's
a long way of saying um please be super
mindful of not creating an other and
they did then of course the world is
uttering X are like this were being
radicals or being the even almost
declared terrorists and all this kind of
stuff but but that's that's the deep
practice the deeper level of non-violent
direct action in a truly Gandhi and kind
of way is not to get triggered by that
and and not to respond with all your
other amel and I'll give you a bit of
other but to actually keep keep open
keep in dialogue and and really shift
from it's all going to shits and we have
a extinction as the first word rebellion
to saying be to avoid extinction we need
because that's what you're saying yeah
and if we co-create regenerate have
contracted everywhere then we won't have
as much extinction as if you don't yeah
we're still committed unfortunately to
lots of species disappearing um but
we're also capable of of slowing that
down drastically and and improving and
vast amount of land and oceans and
that's exciting
yeah I think it's that getting excited
about the positive bit that we we are
the generation that that is called to
transform the human impact on earth and
the only way to do it is to do it
together and not to keep chumming
manatee to bits so like there's so many
things that you've said that feel like
for me are keys and unlocking new
understanding and new possibilities it's
lots for me to go away and think about
and I'm excited to figure out how I
write this up and translate what you
said onto paper yeah I really
yeah I really respect you and respects
your insight and your if it does feel
like you're an L or you are like an
elder of regenerative cultures you have
you have a certain amount of wisdom and
and that wisdom is about us asking these
questions together but it yeah it's
really great to be asking them with you
so thank you that's really thank you
it's really hard to hear positive
feedback we're all kind of used to and
like the slightest amount of criticism
goes in deep and keeps you awake at
night
and and something as lovely as you just
said to me is it doesn't go in so I'm a
friend of mine recently said Daniel you
need to let it in because it nourish you
and so I'm and trying to practice that
right now and thank you so thank you it
was a wonderful conversation and thank
you for everything you do because mm
yeah we're just two different
expressions of the same planetary
process absolutely yeah
yeah I'll be I'll I'll I'll send you a
copy before of what how I've written
everything up before it goes out and
yeah I just thank you just really big
thank you I'm here for to support you
and will I'll stay in touch of like what
we're up to but yeah there was a thing
that you spoke to that I just wanted to
briefly mention before I go about the
vision like what is the vision like
that's been a big piece missing from XR
and I'm a part of a team that's working
on a campaign to bring that into into
the movement of like okay so you're now
asking the questions of like what what
can I do that I can start creating this
this future how can I start creating the
changes that we need and that's going to
be this regenerate 2020 campaign a sort
of movement of movements of regenerative
cultures so we'll see we'll see how it
how it goes that that's reach out to me
and the people from Akalis you know they
network because they that there is a
network of expressions of regenerative
culture across Europe that are quite
chronic grassroots based and and I they
would love to be of help like they
basically we've already like this
wonderful sentence that that um
EF Schumacher the guy who shoe maja
college was named after and he said we
may not be able to raise the winds but
we can set the sails so when the wind
comes were ready and and there's a hell
of a lot of people out there the Center
for alternative technology and and all
the eco villages and all the
permaculture movement that get in touch
with many Holland that Park a network or
I'm Nikole during there they're all
they're all like I mean this is UK for
moment these but they're all already
there they are regenerative cultures and
bringing the kind of people jumped onto
X are but underwear of this just may
exist invisible to each other is yeah
big transformative change that we need
right now we need to see that we've
actually been working on the solution
and the response for 50 years but below
the radar and yeah I have put us above
the rain and now we need to bring that
back yeah so rich building absolutely
wonderful I'll hit stop might just just
pretty really and is it okay if I share
this also with on social media and and
do a little write-up about it or would
you like to do it first through X are
yeah I don't know let me let me ask my
team I think I think what would be what
would be ideal is if we can do a write
up first and then okay I think just
because ya know been nice on my ways
well okay let me know what you team
thinks yeah stop and also I was I was
gonna say because I know that you're
involved with the Schumacher